{"tossups": [{"question": "During World War II, this character's comic strip recruited children into metal recycling crews known as the Junior Commandos. This character was named after a James Whitcomb Riley poem by her creator, cartoonist Harold Gray. For 10 points, name this character who, in a musical adaptation, sings about her \"Hard Knock Life\" and \"Tomorrow.\"", "answer": "Little Orphan <b><u>Annie</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Joseph Haydn composed pieces in this genre named for \"a time of war\" and Horatio Nelson. Leo\u0161 Jan\u00e1\u010dek (<b>lay-OHSH yuh-NAH-chek</b>) used a dead Slavonic language to create the \"Glagolitic\" example of this form, which was used for a piece in B minor by J.S. Bach. For 10 points, name this genre which sets the \"Kyrie\" (<b>KEER-ee</b>-<b>ay</b>), \"Credo,\" and other parts of a liturgy.", "answer": "<b><u>mass</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This specific location is where the <em>Perserschutt</em>, a dump of destroyed ceremonial artifacts, was buried. The Sacred Way ran between Eleusis and the Propylaea, a gate that controlled entrance to this specific location. Many structures in this specific place, including the Erechtheum, were reconstructed by Phidias at the behest of Pericles. For 10 points, name this hill in Athens, the location of the Parthenon.", "answer": "the <b><u>Acropolis</u></b> of Athens [or the <b><u>Cecropia</u></b>; prompt on \u201c<b><u>Athens</u></b>\u201d until \u201cAthens\u201d is read]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Gustave de Beamount and Alexis de Tocqueville originally went to the U.S. to observe these facilities, thoguh Tocqueville wrote <em>Democracy in America</em> instead. Jeremy Bentham proposed the \"panopticon\" design for these facilities. For 10 points, name these facilities which penologists study and which have been home to John Dillinger and Charles Manson.", "answer": "<b><u>prison</u></b>s", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "This President lost several Cabinet members, including Secretary of State Abel Upshur, when a cannon exploded on the <em>USS Princeton</em>. He refused to open mail addressed to the \"Acting President\" after he took office following the death of his popular war hero predecessor. For 10 points, name this man who completed the Presidential term of William Henry Harrison.", "answer": "John <b><u>Tyler</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Members of this group built Bodrum Castle, partly from the ruins of the Mausoleum of Halicarnassus. This organization lost Malta after refusing to let Napoleon\u2019s fleet enter its port. Earlier, they lost the island of Rhodes to Suleiman the Magnificent after a 1522 siege. For 10 points, name this crusading order named for their original mandate of caring for the sick.", "answer": "<b><u>Knights Hospitaller</u></b> [or <b><u>Knights of Saint John</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A major doctrinal influence on this group was Joseph Franklin Rutherford, who reformed the Bible Student associations and promoted its belief that Jesus was crucified on a tree rather than a cross. This group, which traces its founding to Charles Taze Russell, published <em>The Watchtower</em>.  For 10 points, name this sect known for proselytizing and not accepting blood donations.", "answer": "<b><u>Jehovah's Witness</u></b>es", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "In a painting of this man by Paolo Veronese, the old woman Sisygambis confusedly addresses this man\u2019s close friend Hephaestion while begging for mercy. In a depiction of this ruler, a giant scroll in Latin describing the casualties of the battle flies over the two armies fighting. For 10 points, name this Macedonian king who was depicted fighting Darius III in <em>The Battle of Issus</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Alexander</u></b> the Great [or <b><u>Alexander III</u></b> of Macedon]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "These people, who acquired a cult following after the discovery of the \"Joplin photos,\" worked with Ralph Fults and Henry Methvin prior to their death in Bienville, Louisiana. A landmark 1967 film about these people starred Faye Dunaway and Warren Beatty. For 10 points, identify this 1930s criminal pair who were killed in a shootout with police.", "answer": "<b><u>Bonnie</u></b> Parker and <b><u>Clyde</u></b> Barrow [or last names, etc.]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man advocated the \"full dinner pail\" in his second \"front porch campaign\" under the management of Mark Hanna. This man was advised not to go to the Temple of Music at the Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo, where he was fatally shot by Leon Czolgosz (<b>CHOLE-gosh</b>). For 10 points, name this President whose death was followed by the rise of Theodore Roosevelt.", "answer": "William <b><u>McKinley</u></b> <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 6 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1992, this agency launched a program to certify electronic devices, most visibly computer monitors, as efficient, known as EnergyStar. A program administered by this government agency has targeted sites such as Love Canal and is known as Superfund. For 10 points, name this agency created by Richard Nixon that enforces the Clean Water Act and similar laws.", "answer": "<b><u>EPA</u></b> [<b><u>Environmental Protection Agency</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "This man's paper <em>On the Description of Oval Curves</em> came out when he was just 14. He created the first color photograph after showing the primacy of the RGB color system. His distribution of gas molecules was combined with the work of Ludwig Boltzmann. For 10 points, name this physicist who determined that light is a wave and formulated laws of electromagnetism.", "answer": "James Clerk <b><u>Maxwell</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "This city is where the mathematician Hypatia (<b>high-PAY-shuh</b>) was killed by a mob. The Septuagint (<b>sep-TOO-uh-jint</b>) was created in this city, which was home to the largest population of Jews in the world in the first and second centuries BC. For 10 points, name this city which was home to a notable \"library\" and \"lighthouse\" in Classical Egypt.", "answer": "<b><u>Alexandria</u></b> [or <b><u>Eskendereyya</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "The losing Democratic candidate in this state's 2014 race sought to become the first Iraq war veteran to serve as a governor and lost to a ticket containing Boyd Rutherford, the third straight black lieutenant governor in this state. For 10 points, name this state where Anthony Brown lost in an upset to Republican Lawrence Hogan in a bid to succeed Martin O'Malley as governor.", "answer": "<b><u>Maryland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country was the destination of Operation Provide Relief and Operation Restore Hope. The U.S. intervened in this country following the fall of the Siad Barre (<b>see-ODD bah-RAY</b>) regime. A disastrous mission in this country's capital involved two Black Hawk helicopters being shot down. For 10 points, name this country where the U.S. fought the Battle of Mogadishu.", "answer": "<b><u>Somalia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader mediated the Mediterranean Agreements of 1887. His struggle against the Catholic Church throughout the 1870s was known as the Kulturkampf. He instigated a war to take Schleswig and Holstein from Denmark, and used the Ems Dispatch to trigger the Franco-Prussian War. For 10 points, name this Prussian statesman who united the German Empire.", "answer": "Otto von <b><u>Bismarck</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In 2009, voters approved an amendment in this organization's constitution that replaced the unanimity requirement with a \u201cdouble majority\u201d requirement for many policies. The Maastricht Treaty created this group and gave the criteria necessary for countries to adopt its common currency. For 10 points, name this organization of sovereign states, many of whom use the euro.", "answer": "<b><u>European Union</u></b> [or <b><u>EU</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Mark Kurlansky's popular-press <em>World History</em> of this good describes how the Taghaza mine produced it in the medieval Sahara desert. This chemical compound was traded in silence in pre-modern West Africa, where its value per pound was equal to a pound of gold. For 10 points, name this mineral which was useful for preserving meat and balancing diets.", "answer": "rock <b><u>salt</u></b> [or <b><u>halite</u></b>; or <b><u>sodium chloride</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Along with \u201cliberty,\u201d this good names the Russian revolutionary group that split into the</u></b> <b><u>People\u2019s Will and Black Repartition. Economist Henry George proposed a single tax on</u></b> <b><u>this good and the abolition of all other taxes in his book (+)</u></b> <em><b>Progress and Poverty</b></em><b>. The 18<u>th</u>-century French economic school known as (*)</b> Physiocracy argued that wealth was entirely derived from development of this good. For 10 points, name this good necessary for farming.", "answer": "<b><u>land</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "<b><u>This woman signed herself \"FWOTSC\" in a letter objecting to the term \"nine old men.\"</u></b> <b><u>This woman was the majority leader of the Arizona State Senate prior to her appointment</u></b> <b><u>to the (+)</u> Maricopa County Superior Court in 1975. She was replaced by Samuel Alito after retiring in 2005. She was nominated in 1981 to take the seat of (*)</b> Potter Stewart, by President Reagan. For 10 points, name this first woman to serve on the U.S. Supreme Court.", "answer": "Sandra Day <b><u>O'Connor</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This loser of the Battle of Valcour Island fell under suspicion for marrying Peggy</u></b> <b><u>Shippen. This man supported Ethan Allen's Green Mountain Boys in the capture of Fort</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Ticonderoga and was a key American presence at the Battle of (*)</b> Saratoga. Later, this man conspired with John Andre to surrender West Point. For 10 points, identify this American  Revolutionary  War  general  whose  name  is  now  synonymous  with  treason.", "answer": "Benedict <b><u>Arnold</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country celebrates the two-week-long Dashain (DAH-shayn) festival every fall. In</u></b> <b><u>the 1980s, this country took in over a hundred thousand Lhotshampa (LOTE-sahm-pa)</u></b> <b><u>refugees. This country has been subject to unrest in the (+)</u> Terai (teh-RYE) region, which it shares with India, and it was the only officially (*)</b> Hindu country in the world until its monarchy was abolished in 2008. For 10 points, name this Himalayan country governed from Kathmandu.", "answer": "<b><u>Nepal</u></b>[Federal Democratic Republic of <b><u>Nepal</u></b>; or Sanghiya Loktantrik Ganatantra <b><u>Nepal</u></b>]", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>The winner of this sporting event is awarded the Harley J. Earl Trophy, and Sterling</u></b> <b><u>Marlin is the most recent back-to-back winner, doing so in 1994 and 1995. Dale (+)</u> Jarrett is the most recent to win it from the pole. Its 2014 winner was Dale (*) </b>Earnhardt Jr., who drove the #21 Chevrolet to Victory Lane. For 10 points, name this automobile race, the first event in NASCAR's annual Sprint Cup series, and which takes place at a namesake track in Northern Florida.", "answer": "<b><u>Daytona</u></b> 500", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>Like Pope Pius IX, this leader was presented with a Golden Telephone by the ITT</u></b> <b><u>Corporation, and this man imprisoned the leaders of the Conspiracy of the Pure. This man</u></b> <b><u>came to power after cancelling an election in which he was opposed by the Orthodox Party</u></b> <b><u>and the Authentic Party. This man overthrew (+)</u>Gerardo Machado as leader of the Sargents\u2019 Revolt, and was overthrown by the</b> (*) July 26th movement. For 10 points, name this dictator of Cuba overthrown by Fidel Castro.", "answer": "Fulgencio <b><u>Batista</u></b> y Zald\u00edvar", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An extensive study of these people was compiled by Thomas McKenney and James Hall</u></b> <b><u>in the 1830s. These people are the subject of Helen Hunt Jackson's book</u> </b><em><b><u>A Century of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Dishonor</u></b></em><b><u>. Scott O'Dell wrote about a woman from this general group of people in (+)</u></b> <em><b>Island of the Blue Dolphins</b></em><b>, and these general people are the subjects of most books by (*) </b>Vine Deloria and Sherman Alexie. For 10 points, name these people who appear in pre-Columbian North American histories.", "answer": "American <b><u>Indians</u></b> [or <b><u>Native Americans</u></b>, etc.]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Critic Fred Hobson mused that this technology would have made writing the novels of</u></b> <b><u>William Faulkner impossible. This technology was named by Stuart Cramer after early</u></b> <b><u>models by John Gorrie and Edward Elis were perfected in 1902 in Buffalo, by Willis (+)</u></b> <b>Carrier. These devices allowed for the post-war economic and population boom in the (*) </b>South. For 10 points, name these devices which use freon or other liquids to dehumidify and cool buildings.", "answer": "<b><u>air conditioner</u></b>s [or word forms]  <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 6 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>This man's National Security Advisor McGeorge Bundy was one of the \"wise men\" who</u></b> <b><u>advised him, in contrast to the young \"Whiz Kids\" who were chronicled in David</u></b>  <b><u>Halberstam's book about this man's administration,</u> </b><em><b><u>The</u> </b></em><b><u>(+)</u></b> <em><b>Best and the Brightest</b></em><b>. He was President during what Theodore White dubbed (*) </b>\"Camelot.\" For 10 points, name this President who said \"ask what you can do for your country\" at his inauguration, three years before his assassination in Dallas.  ANSWER: John Fitzgerald <b><u>Kennedy</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}